this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program okay so welcome
listeners to another episode on software
engineering radio this time we talk with
the human pitler about agile product
management so welcome woman hi Martin
hello great to have you here can you
introduce yourself to our listeners hi
i'm broman i work is an independent
consultant specialised in scrum and
agile product management i'm the author
of two books on scrum my most recent one
is called agile project management with
scrum creating products that customers
love when I first came across agile
practices in 1999 and I coached my first
agile project in 2001 ever since then
I've been involved in helping
organizations leverage agile methods
particularly scrum and in recent years
I've primarily focused on the role of
the product owner in helping product
managers understand what their place in
this brave new agile world is and can
you tell us a little bit about what is
agile product management from your point
of view actual product management in my
mind differs from traditional product
management approaches in a number of
areas so I think it's important to
recognize that it is something genuinely
different or genuinely new it's not just
a slightly different way of carrying out
product management practices so that the
five areas that I feel our cue to
understand how an agile scrum based
product management approach differs from
a traditional old-school approach in
those five areas are the roles that we
use the collaboration we see between the
different roles the early upfront
activities how products are discovered
in how product functionality is defined
and finally how we leverage customer and
user feedback so those are five areas
where we see significant differences
if we look at the rolls then
traditionally we have the responsibility
for coming up with a vision for new
product and turning that vision into a
successful product its distributed
across different roles different people
different shoulders typically someone
like a product market here would maybe
come up with a product on Sept would
engage in market research activities
maybe carry out some business analysis
I'm a product manager would then take
the product concept and derive a
requirement specification from it in a
project manager would then run the
actual development project so different
people are engaged in the process the
process at different points in time and
they essentially handoff work results
now in an agile project management
approach certainly in a skrub context
and we have one person the product owner
who is in charge of the product and who
leads the project so we in a way
centralize those responsibilities that
were distributed across many different
roles and we now have one person that in
a way holds together the entire value
stream can you give us a little bit more
detail about what what the product owner
role Instagram is what does it look like
what responsibilities are connected to
it can you give us a bit more details
yes the product owner is I find a very
interesting role in in scrum so I you
know just to recap very briefly they are
only three roles in scrum so we don't
have that many the product owner the
scrum master in the team and sometimes
we say well you know all those three
roles really should should should work
together effectively and collaborate so
therefore be able to have what's called
the scrum team that encompasses all the
other three roles now change waiver
rights about the the product owner role
in the scrum guide in this since the
scrum guide is you know in a way that
the reference booklet for scrum I find
it helpful to take a look and see what
Ken writes now in he says that the
product owner is the one and only person
who's responsible for managing the
product backlog and ensuring the value
of the work the
team performs and he also says this
person maintains the product backlog and
ensures that it is visible to everyone
now when I first read this this little
definition I thought it sounds rather
harmless in off my I think that sort of
that's people's first impression when
they come across the product owner role
they say yeah yeah okay someone from the
business side of someone who someone
represents the business or the customer
you know something a little bit like an
on-site customer ok whatever however if
you if you if you look more closely into
the role if you look into the roles
Authority and responsibility in the
duties you see that it is actually a
very complex role with a with many
diverse responsibilities so the product
owner is is typically responsible for
what I would call strategic and
technical aspects of managing a product
so the product owner typically leads
product discovery but also helps to
identify and describe requirements make
sure that the product backlog is ready
ready for the next sprint learning
meeting and engages in product planning
in envisioning and prior drug mapping
and the individual typically decides on
the content of a release carries out
release planning brief you work results
it provides feedback to the team and
managers customers users and
stakeholders so it's as I said a and a
diverse multifaceted and often
challenging role that the product owner
duties often cut across the
responsibilities of existing roles such
as the product market tear product
manager and project manager so often
doesn't fit easily into existing
organizational structures do you think
that just one person inside a team can
carry all those different roles into one
one new product owner role or do you
think of multiple people playing this
role or talking to each other or having
a team was something like that that's an
interesting question now scrum says that
there has to be one person who takes on
who plays the product owner role now in
my experience one product owner can only
look at the limited number of teams and
you know I feel you know two to three
teams is a fairly fairly face it's a
fairly lot of fairly large number of
teams to look after sided the product
owner world typically doesn't scale
beyond two to three teams now if you
develop a product that requires a larger
project with more teams you obviously
need more product owners so in that
sense yes you can have more product
owners and those product owners will
then collaborate this part of a product
owner team however one of those product
owners would have to be the overall or
chief product owner in charge of the
entire product and the entire project so
what you'd like to avoid is working with
what's sometimes called a product or in
a committee a committee a group of
product owners where it's not clear who
has the final say if no consensus can be
reached okay so the I remember I don't
know if it's Kent Beck or so talking
about the the the on-site customer this
this is one voice to the team so
speaking with one voice the team and
collecting all the different opinions
from from different people's into one
stream of stories priorities features he
would like to have the idea we have with
the product owners very similar the
product owner really is the person who
ultimately decides what goes into a
release who decides in which order the
items in the product backlog I've worked
on so the product owner is the ultimate
decision maker with anything with regard
to what the product looks like and what
the product does I write in my new book
that the product owner it's a little bit
special with regards the product success
I mean ultimately we call product owner
scrum master in team all-big since grown
because they are because because they
all have skin in the game they they all
responsible for making sure that a
successful product is created but the
product owner is particularly
responsible for the product success and
making sure that value is created and in
hence it's only fair to make sure that
the product owner is adequately
empowered has the authority
to decides on the contents of off the
release okay so would you agree that
this for me it sounds like like this guy
is um it's pretty responsible form for
many things he has to decide on the
business value so what is vailable to
the team what is not available to the
team or to the product to the customer
he has to decide and which steps which
priorities to realize is how to how to
pack these things into small releases
and stuff like that sensor like a pretty
hard job would you agree I'd agree that
it is a challenging job and it's a very
multifaceted job so the product owner
has to foreigners often have to take on
a diverse range of responsibilities and
I think it's also very interesting when
you think about it that scrum
centralizes responsibilities that are
traditionally scattered across many
different roles in one role now the
reason we do this is to make sure that
there is one person who's in charge of
the product who's in charge of the value
stream and you know ideally looks after
the product across multiple releases if
not manages the products life cycle
Kennish Weber writes in his second book
that the focus of the product owner
should be on return on investment now if
you think about how long it takes for
return on investment meant to be to
actually manifest itself then that
typically requires the product to be in
the market for some time maybe a year
maybe two maybe even a little bit longer
so if you want to measure the product
owners job in a way by the return on
investment and reaching return on
investment goals and that means that the
product owner has to look after the
product for an extended period of time
so it's for a being a product owner is
RFU being the product owner is a very
important job as a job that and provides
a lot of visibility or should provide a
lot of visibility if you're the product
owner for a strategically important
product you may have sponsorship from
senior management from the CEO your
managing director him or herself so
again I think it's important to
recognize that product owners have to be
adequately empowered in order to be able
to take on the many duties the many
responsibilities they have so let's
let's take a look a little bit more
detail what would what these product
owner would you read us your book I
think if I remember that correctly is
entitled edge a product development or
product management and creating products
that customers love so how do you how do
you ensure that the customers will love
your product if I'm tempted to say
you'll have to go and read my book to
really understand how to do it but I can
certainly try to summarize a few key
techniques to make sure that we create
products that hopefully customers will
will enjoy will love the first thing
that I suggest in my book is to make
sure that there is a shared product
vision available so that's product
owners from Aston team have a vision
that guides their development effort and
that roughly describes this granted a
coarse-grained level what the product
should look like and do I think that's
very important you know to have a goal
have a commonly agreed a shared goal to
shoot for and the second I think it's
it's key to you to involve customers and
users in the development process and in
the way the best way to do this in an
agile context is a to invite customers
and users at least selected customers
and users to the sprint review meetings
let them see the demo of the product
increment let them engage in the
discussion participate in the discussion
ask them for feedback ask them if they
if they like what they Chester although
well that what they what they've just
seen ask them for ideas how the product
could be improved I mean huge use the
conversation to adapt the product
backlog and adapt the product in and
drive the development of future product
increments and secondly release product
increments as early in as frequently as
you can get them out you know I mean if
you concern about keeping a competitive
advantage you don't necessary
to release to the whole world world
maybe again there's only a selected
group of customers and users you release
an early probably incrementally maybe in
form of an alpha or beta version but
that should be then are adequately
tested and documented of course in a in
a scrum context in again by listening to
the response that comes back from from
those customers and users that test an
early product increments in in its
target environment and that will help
you to adapt to your product
and make sure you're developing the
right product so the key for me really
is to integrate customers and users
early on in the development process and
keep them engaged keep them involved in
the development off of the product now
the last thing I'd like to recommend is
to focus on what I call that the minimal
marketable product a product that has a
small feature set the minimum
functionality necessary in order to
market and sell the product and that's
so important because it allows you to
reduce your time to market and the
shorter your time to market is that is
the quicker you receive the actual
market response now it's all good and
well to invites selected customers and
users to your sprint briefly meetings
that's great and it's also great to ship
early prod of increments to may be
selected customers and users but they
may or may not be completely
representative for the wider market
you're aiming for so by actually making
your products accessible available to
the general public to your entire market
population so to speak and you get the
real feedback and you see if the product
you're building is the right product or
not and that's a technique that Google
has has employed very successfully is
this completely different from you
mentioned Google from a company like for
example Apple doing all these fancy new
product development stuff completely
secretly
inside the company and then goes to
public when it's when it's final I don't
think so
when you look at
you look at Google then you'll find that
Google has different forms of confident
confidentiality when it comes to new
products sorry the products like will
use that anybody can see at an early
stage like even me then their products
that are a little bit more confidential
by Google has a specific program to
which a Google employees can invites
close friends and family members and
then there are top secret programs like
the Google Chrome browser development
project the Android project and similar
projects that Google keeps on the wraps
and and Google then still uses the
technique of releasing product
increments early and frequently but only
in terms of internal releases so Google
uses its own employees as a sounding
bass to help drive the development of
the product and make sure that the
development team doesn't get stuck in a
rut and you know gets good feedback from
people that are not involved in the in
the project on a day-to-day basis mmm
and if I transfer this to tool to to my
contacts doing mostly business
application development inside a company
an insurance company or whatever so I
could imagine putting putting a beta or
whatever true to to small group people
trying that out um but it's it's a lot
more difficult to use this this beat up
version in real protection usage because
put this software in production usage it
requires a huge huge amount of whatever
putting databases and data to all these
new product versions and stuff like that
so you cannot use the regular protection
version of the system together with a
brand new beta version so how do you
ensure that you get get real good
feedback from those guys I think the the
scenario you just mentioned show is that
the the environment the infrastructure
is optimized for infrequent
deployments of large chunks of
functionality which you know spend the
case in most IT organizations that I've
I've been in touch with and now I
remember working with one specific
clients a few years back credit-card
company and we we found it difficult to
release early for the very same reasons
for the same reasons that you just
mentioned but what we did is we invited
representatives from the user community
to come to the sprint review meetings
and we invited them to provide feedback
on the demo and we also asked them to
come and attend sprint review meetings
on a regular basis to create some
continuity and that was that turned out
to be very helpful it was very valuable
for everyone including the product owner
to receive that feedback it certainly
helped to move the product in the right
direction and it was also very
beneficial for the users because they
really they solved what the product
would look like and they could better
anticipate the impact and new
functionality had and their day-to-day
work but you would also agree that that
it's more important to release
frequently and so if you have the chance
to say ok if I like the chance to
release the Sprint the sprint result to
the community instead of just inviting
the users you would always prefer
releasing the software with you I
probably would have a preference to
release software early and frequently I
think it's you know ideally I'd like to
do both I'd like to have users in
customers present because that gives you
the ability to facilitate qualitative
feedback to engage in a conversation you
know you know the Sprint review meeting
the demo provides a nice context so you
both look at the product increment and
then you can engage in a conversation
you can talk about what we've just seen
you can talk about what works well what
doesn't work so well in identify
improvement potential you don't get that
conversation you don't get this dialogue
if you if you deploy if you release
however if you release you get more
quantitative feedback you know you you
find out better which
defects and in bugs are hidden in in the
product users will will end up using the
product in unanticipated ways that may
cause all sorts of opportunities and
problems and again you wouldn't get this
type of feedback if you only showed your
customers and users the product in the
sprint review meeting so you know I
suggest you both whenever you can do
bugs okay and see so coming back to
these say you mentioned the minimum
marketable feature which you can release
or which provides a business value how
do you or how does the the product owner
what about criteria is can you use to to
decide what is a minimal releasable
feature or mineral marketable feature
and what it's not so let me explain my
background sometimes when I talk to
people about this kind of agile
development they argue especially the
the product owner people they argue oh I
have this feature and I can release this
feature only at a whole just this
feature and the team said oh we need
half year to Reese to build that feature
and this is not what I what I imagine
with a minimal marketable feature what a
well such a feature should be so how do
you how do you help those guys to find
out what what really small features can
be and how they can cut down their
features into small units our preferred
the term minimal marketable product it
obviously is a deliberate reference to
determine you've just mentioned minimum
marketable feature set which was coined
by a book published in 2004 software by
numbers now the idea in this book is
that you truly identify a group of
features a set of features that you can
somehow mark it somehow sell and then
you're incrementally in a way sell your
product while you develop it and even
though I find that fascinating very
attractive in theory I've found it very
difficult to put it in practice hence I
find it I find it more helpful to say
okay now we want to build a new product
so you want to build a new iPhone kill
what would be the essential features the
essential product attributes that this
product would have to realize in order
to be a market success and I'm not
looking for a long list of 20 25 30
features you know that's easy to
generate we'll just sit down and
brainstorm for five minutes and whoops
we've got a long list I'm looking at I'm
looking for the three I'm looking for
three three four five top features that
must be there to provide a value added
and to give us a unique selling
proposition and entice customers to buy
the product now that that is all part of
envisioning the product in creating the
product vision as far as I'm concerned
and I find it very interesting that the
scrum literature so far has been largely
silent on what the product lesion is in
scrum we've said oh you need a product
mission and it goes right back to the
very first scrum book which was
published in 2002 but we firm we've been
very secretive about what the vision
should really look like what kind of
questions it should answer what the
qualities of a good question vision in
scrum should be so I think it's
essential to to take some time before
you start with the first Sprint's to
think about what kind of product are we
building and it all starts with with
with asking yourself who are our
customers who are the target customers
the people that we'd like to buy our
product and who do we believe will
actually use our product who do we
believe the users are and which of their
needs is the product going to address
which which which problems which which
province is the product gonna solve for
those users and customers which jobs is
it going to do for them and that helps
you then to identify the right
functionality in again for me the key
here is to very focus on on those
features that must be present to ensure
product success and it's I find it's the
opposite approach that particularly
large companies tend to take where often
when a product is conceived or envisions
people try to think of a perfect product
with loads of functionality that there's
many different things and you know that
could be the product that is available
maybe in a years or two years time after
you've shipped version 11.5 - and 2.5
but what you'd really like to do is to
say okay out of all those out of all
this long-term dream what is really the
smallest thing that you could build in
ship within a competitive time frame and
that still creates enough value so it's
it's it's usable for the users and
customers will want to will want to buy
it even if it's maybe contains a lot
less functionality than then other
products in the same area area right
there's absolutely right you know I've
mentioned building an iPhone killer look
at what Apple did with the original
iPhone that shipped in 2007 when the
phone first came out many many critics
said it's it's very limited thing he
writes an iPod you you happen to be able
to make phone calls and by the way the
voice quality is poor and it doesn't
have this and it doesn't have that and
it's true you know I mean it didn't have
him you know you there are many things
that the iPhone couldn't do when it was
first launched no copy-and-paste
took out for two years to rectify this
problem I believe you couldn't even send
text messages to multiple recipients but
I don't think I don't think that was a
problem that Apple deliberately
neglected or left out some functionality
actually think that gave Apple a
competitive advantage they didn't make
the mistake to say all now we look at
all this all the competitor products and
copy all the functionality that they
provide plus more functionality on top
of it thinking you know bigger must be
better in more functionality means oh
you know customers are more likely to
buy the product they really focused on a
small narrow target group and that's one
of the key tricks if you want to get to
a minimal marketable product that you
clearly define your target group so they
only focused on the consumer group
within their customers space and said
okay all those business and enterprise
users where a lot of money can be
for now just not target them and even
within that group they were looking for
people that maybe had a certain affinity
to Apple and way into design and stylish
gadgets and and those people just loved
the iPhone and that built the success
and what Apple then did is for the basis
of the success what Apple then did is
they increment they've they've
incrementally enhanced the product since
they first brought it out state they
made an incremental update in terms of
hardened software in 2008 and then again
an incremental update in 2009 so you
know leaving functionality out of the
product focusing on a narrow target
group group of target customers a key
ways to achieve a product with minimum
functionality the you would if I
summarize that you would agree that the
most important part for the product
owner is not finding all the features
that you would like to get but finding
the right ones or the most important
ones absolutely right yes and I think
it's you know again which has changed
the process when you look at product
definition requirements engineering in
an agile context then it's the opposite
of what we do traditionally
traditionally we try to define the
product up front as completely in as
much detail and as precisely as we
possibly can why well because we'll need
a requirement specification that should
be more or less frozen and yes you can
have requirements changes but they're
strictly controlled and they should be
the exception now in in an agile context
the whole process works completely
differently we we start literally with a
sketch evasion we say hey wouldn't it be
a cool idea you know when we're building
this kind of product and here are the
three to five top features those are
going to be the customers and users that
gonna buy it and this is why they will
want to buy it and use the product and
then then then we use that vision to
create an initial product backlog that
will also be very sketchy most of the
items in the product backlog will be
highly under specified and and we then
use early customer in user feedback to
design how exactly what exactly the
product is gonna look like and what
exactly it's going to do so rather than
making all those assumptions about the
product functionality the looking for
the user experience upfront we do it as
we go along and the key thing again is
to integrate customers and users into
the development process and leverage
their feedback to drive the development
of the product do you think that you
need to look at the usability aspects of
those features when when building these
first increments as well certainly I
think usability plays place a key part
in developing a product now I would I
would recommend that key aspects offer
products usability are addressed as part
of envisioning the product so I would
expect that individuals depending on how
you manage your ideation and early
innovation management activities in your
company's individuals are given some
time and innovation budget or that the
scrum team together engages in those
early activities that individuals play
around and then create prototypes and
then also visual prototypes are created
that explore the user interface that
explore how the whole user user
experience piece should play out so I
would expect that areas of the product
that are important to the product
success where the product is supposed to
excel in areas that will be difficult to
change at a later point in time that
exhibit a certain amount of risk I
explored early on it's part of the
visioning process infirmity types
typically throw away prototypes and then
certainly also by prioritizing the
product back of the right way and making
user experience related requirements
high-priority in the only sprints ok so
um if we go back to the to the role of
the product owner and his
responsibilities we talked briefly about
putting all these small features or
maybe user stories however do you call
them in the product backlog and
developing the product backlog for the
different iterations and Sprint's
releases so can you tell us a little bit
more about this this work with the
product backlog
product backlog yes so maybe maybe it's
it's it's a worthwhile exercise that we
briefly reflect on what the product
backlog is and the product backlog is is
really something very very simple it is
it is the outstanding amount of work
necessary to bring the product to life
so it contains it's a key of all the
work that needs to be done in order to
create a successful product most of the
items in the product backlog are
typically related to the products of
products functionality and describe the
products functionality are hence
requirements but you could have other
items in there as well including fixing
bugs defects or creating other
deliverables that may be necessary so so
that's what it is it's a it's a list of
outstanding work however in addition to
just being a list it should fulfill four
qualities that Mike owned and I have
started to call it the deep qualities so
just a list of outstanding work is not
enough to qualify as a product backlog
you could take a traditional requirement
specification and coffee paint and copy
and paste it into a spreadsheet and then
say hey you know it's a list of
outstanding work here's our product
backlog
well that trick doesn't quite work since
the product backlog has to be detailed
appropriately and that's the first
quality and that means the high priority
items have to be more detailed all fine
grains have to be more specific
then lower priority wants the low
priority items can be pretty big quite
sketchy and under specified and very
cool screens the second property of the
of the product backlog is that it
emerges so it's it's content evolves
throughout the project as I try to
explain earlier we move away from this
idea in an agile environment that
requirements are fixed or that we can
can can precisely anticipate predict at
an early stage what the product should
look like in doing detail rather we say
okay based on the custom and user
feedback we learn more about their needs
and how we can best
address their needs and therefore what
exactly the product should look like can
do so new requirements are discovered
and new requirements are entered into
the product backlog as I said throughout
the project so the product backlog has a
very organic qualities it's it's by no
means fixed or frozen in any way and
then finally the other two qualities
which are probably a little bit more
well known are the product backlog has
to be estimated its items have to be
sized and it has to be prioritized so
all the items in the product backlog
have to be ordered so those are the four
qualities of off the product backlog
just just a question but you mentioned
the the the items and the product
backlog of different size and of some of
them are very detailed and precise and
some of them are rather sketchy so how
do you ensure that the sketchy ones are
estimated or does the estimation
requirement just focuses on the only
high priority items no in fact the idea
we have is that you estimate the entire
product backlog what happens is that
your lower priority items will be will
receive a large estimates and be that
there's more uncertainty around the
estimate so that the quality of the
estimates will be poorer than the the
quality of an estimate of a high
priority item but don't forget that the
estimates of Pro backlog items are
exclusively used in scrum to aid release
planning to understand how far if we
come in to create a forecasts about how
long it's going to take to finish or how
much functionality you'll be able to
deliver within a given time and budget
frame so we don't use estimates in the
product backlog with estimates of
requirements the same way they're used
in traditional project management so
what happens is that as product backlog
items worked on that decomposed that
refines they're broken down into smaller
items they are made more specific and
those new items are then estimated again
and in therefore so you over time you
see the
back row and you see that the team
becomes more confident in the estimates
obviously also because the team learns
about how much work it actually is to
implement product backlog items and this
learning then feeds back into estimating
product backlog items and estimating
product backlog items forms part of
managing or grooming the product backlog
and managing the product backlog
grooming the product backlog is an
ongoing process so it's not that once at
the beginning of the project before the
first sprint you go over the product
backlog and yes they made all the items
and you prioritize it and you make sure
it's ready and then that's it you're
done now because you have customer
feedback and user feedback influencing
the product packaging because
requirements emerge and because items
are taken out of the product back up the
team confuse items product backlog items
pulls them into the sprint and
transforms them into product increments
the product backlog needs to be
constantly at least regularly grooms and
and managed and and managing grooming
the product backlog is a collaborative
process in scrum it's it's teamwork
so it's something the product owner has
to lead and drive but it's also a
process where scrum master in team
members and as appropriate stakeholders
including customers and users
participate in we've before ready
mentioned one specific aspect of product
backlog grooming where customers and
users are involved and that's um that's
in the spring Rica meeting when you
discuss the demo you discuss the prod of
increment and users and customers may
have good ideas about new new product
functionality new requirements so you
said that the the product owner is
responsible for prioritizing all these
these items what about these kind of
non-functional requirements that every
project is now non-functional
requirements are very interesting in a
number with regards to a number of
aspects the first the first thing to
notice is that non-functional
requirements come in sort of two loose
groups I would say there are
non-functional requirements that are
related to the user experience such as
usability
requirements style and design
requirements for instance and their
non-functional requirements that are
related to the operational qualities of
the system things like performance
robustness scalability interoperability
and in others now some of those
non-functional requirements can be
global in nature and that means they
basically apply to all the other
functional items in the product backlog
things like you know again if you think
about the mobile phone being able to
make and receive calls for instance
those would be functional requirements
functional properties in global alone
functional requirements would apply to
virtually all other functional
requirements and then you get some local
non-functional requirements that only
apply to one or two specific items in
the product backlog functional items in
the product backlog now I I quite like
to work with structured product backlog
and I quite like to work with
hierarchical product backlogs and what I
do in order to deal with particularly
global non-functional requirements is to
create a separate area in the product
backlog can be a separate column in a
spreadsheet or it can be just part of
you from a backlog task board if you
have a physical product backlog that you
use and I put the the key global will
put the global non-functional
requirements in there and typically you
only get about a handful or so of global
non-functional requirements and I keep
them there so that they're visible and
we don't forget about them
because obviously they have a big impact
they have a big impact on the user
experience and user experience is
related to how likely it is that users
are going to use the product unlikely
reach the customers are going to buy the
product they also have an impact on
architecture and technology choice and
therefore on total cost of ownership and
life expectancy of the product so they
have a big they have a big economic
impact but what I don't do is I don't
ask the team to estimate those global
non-functional requirements I rather
integrate them into the definition of
done or state and the definition of done
that those global non-functional
requirements have to be met so they
create cost they create an effort it's
not free to have those global
non-functional requirements but the way
the effort is accounted for is
indirectly by estimate
the functional requirements the global
non-functional requirements applied to
so that's that's one way of doing it and
I found that quite quite quite quite a
helpful quite an effective way of
dealing with global non-functional
requirements local non-functional
requirements how you deal with them is a
little bit dependent on the requirements
description technique that you use if
you use user stories then you can simply
capture those requirements as
constraints and attach them to your
individual cards your story cards and
I've also seen teams capture
non-functional local non-functional
requirements acceptance criteria of
stories so that's that's also something
that some teams do how would you how
would you deal with the with changes to
these global non-functional requirements
so after half a year someone decides to
oh we we need to modify the look and
feel of the application slightly would
you say it's it's it's just a normal
task that the product owner can
prioritize into the sprint backlogs so
before I answer your question at me and
maybe make another thing something else
clear what would have tried to explain
earlier is that we try to delay
decisions about the details of the
product functionality until more
information becomes available in until
we receive feedback from customers and
users and that's true for most aspects
of the product but it shouldn't be true
for the critical global non-functional
requirements say you want to build a new
mobile phone then certain non-functional
requirements such as weight such as size
and robustness will be critical will be
critical to the product success it will
be critical to the product design will
be critical to the choice of materials
the architecture you use so you've got
to make those choices early on and do
enough prototyping as part of creating
the product vision to to be fairly
confident to feel fairly confident that
you've made the right choices so don't
delay detailing detailing global
functional requirements do the opposite
so they're the big exception to the
general rule of oh you know just delay
requirements and delay the specifics of
the product for as long as you can I
think it's perfectly normal that to a
certain extend also usability and user
interface and user experience related
requirements evolve and it particularly
that the details do emerge that's okay
and it's also okay that once the
products been in production or once the
products been released
somebody says would like to make some
changes it just needs to be then planned
in and the way I do this is that I use
for droid map once the first version has
been introduced into the market
successfully to capture ideas for future
releases to look ahead for the next two
to three releases for the next maybe 12
18 24 months max so that customers uses
that the business has an idea how the
product is likely to grow so I attempt
to restrict the initial visioning
activities in the original product
vision to the first version and then I
tend to use the product roadmap to carry
out essentially product planning and I
see so this leads to the discussion of
release cycles I think what do you think
how do you define this the scope of a
release for me the the scope of a
release is defined by the product vision
in the initial product backlog certainly
of version 1.0 product version 1.0 and
then of later product versions the
contents the scope is defined by the
product roadmap so that's the way I work
ultimately as the product owner
it's the entire scrum team whenever you
discover an idea for your product for
your release you should ask yourself if
this idea is truly essential is it truly
critical to achieve product success if
it is well then it should be part of the
release if it isn't it's maybe a good
idea but it is irrelevant so I wouldn't
even bother putting it into the product
backlog some people think well you know
it's such a shame to waste good ideas
and let's just put it right at the
bottom of the product backlog
this is where it stays sometimes for
months or years but you know I'm quite a
big fan of concise product backlogs
short product backlogs so I just tend to
say well you know if it's not relevant
for this for this release or this
version then it's just not bother about
it because who now it's the only thing
that's certain about the future is that
it's uncertain we don't know exactly if
the products going to be a success we
don't know exactly how the next version
is going to be received in the
marketplace let's just wait for that
first before we exactly decide what
should go into the next into the next
versions so the product vision and the
product void map should facilitate
deciding what goes into a release and
how do you define the the timeframe for
aliso a huge huge amount of Atlanteans I
mean completely different timeframes for
relief is some of them releases every
three months
some of them releases every month some
of them are releasing every day what do
you think it's just depending on your
business or and does it have an impact
on how you deal with the product backlog
think it does depend to a certain extent
on your business certainly on your
business model it does depend on the
technologies you use the type of product
you're building if you build a web-based
product then it's certainly much easier
to release very frequently then but you
develop embedded software it's a little
bit more difficult and you release
cycles maybe a little bit longer similar
if you develop an iPhone application
then you know what stops you from
releasing the next version quickly
whereas if you developed for instance a
healthcare product then you know you'll
have to go through some sort of form of
certification and comply to you
regulatory requirements before you can
you can you can ship it before you can
launch it the general recommendation you
find in the agile books is to stick to
three to six months when it comes to
with regards to the lengths off of
projects and particularly in the seconds
XP book came back makes an interesting I
find an interesting recommendation and
he says well if your projects take
longer then use quarterly cycles use
quarterly cycles to subdivide your
project and make sure you have at least
one release in every quarterly cycle so
that's something I recommend too and I
find very helpful as a general rule of
thumb now how long it actually takes you
to finish
your project ends to deliver the amount
the amount of functionality you want to
deliver that's that's an interesting
question and the traditional approach is
to look at the requirements and to
analyze the requirements and based on
the requirements you have created what
packages and tasks and then do some
dependency analysis maybe some critical
path analysis assign activities to
individuals and get the estimates from
individuals for those activities and
there's a number crunching and you get a
schedule and then you also get a budget
you also get the cost the likely cost
that will be incurred by developing this
this product now if you if you want to
employ this approach in a natural
context certainly and scrum you'll hit
one problem and that problem is that the
product backlog is dynamic it changes it
grows it's very organic so yes you can
analyze the contents of the product
backlog at the beginning of the project
but you know that in two three four
Sprint's time those contents will have
changed because your product will
probably will have evolved so I find
this approach very difficult in a
natural context hence I prefer to ask
what is the window of opportunity what
is the timeframe when we need to ship
this product either because otherwise we
believe we won't be able to sell as many
products as we need to or because simply
this is when the business needs the new
IT application this is when marketing
needs the new web application they need
it in three to four months time that's
the window of opportunity and that
window of opportunity is found based on
the product vision you look at the
product vision you look at what kind of
or do you want to build it I also quite
like to do a little bit of competitive
analysis as part of the visioning
activities so if you develop a
commercial product that gives you an
idea for about a desirable launch
timeframe now once you know the window
of opportunity and the type of products
you're about to build
you can then think about who needs to
work on on the project and how big is
that should the project be how many
teams will you have to use and that
gives you an initial budget assuming
that
the decisive cost factor widget I guess
typically is in software development in
other words I quite like to time box
releases I like to work with a release
time box and let the functionality vary
you may decide to also fix the budget
but I don't necessarily think that I
don't think that's necessary you know
I'd like to establish an early budget
range as I said and then just simply see
how fast you progress and then make a
trade-off decision and say ok are we
going to ship with less functionality
will be going to increase the budget and
maybe add a Ruby expert or a Java expert
to the team to increase the team's
velocity and in the end of the
prioritization of the product backlog is
correct and matches the business value
you always guarantee that you get the
best for your money right right I would
say if if you've done a good job in
visioning the the product and if you've
done a good job involving customers and
users early on in the development
process you're very likely to build
something that is valuable the thing you
have to then make sure is that you have
a good package so that you give users a
product that is truly usable and that is
hopefully a joy to use so you know again
assuming that we're building a new
mobile phone the certain features a
mobile phone has to have now I mentioned
that the iPhone the original iPhone
shipped without the ability to send
multiple text messages to multiple
recipients so you can thin out certain
areas of your product functionality you
can thin out certain features but you
still need to provide a certain feature
set in order to create the necessary
value and make people buy the product
but that's then really part of the
release planning process and release
planning is something that the product
owner should lead and it's something
that the team in the scrum master and
also stakeholders engaging the best
point in time to have those
conversations and make the decisions is
again the sprint review meeting as you
clearly understand how far you've come
at the end of the Sprint you've seen the
demo
and you can then together you've got the
right people present hopefully this from
master and the product owner the team
custom end-user representatives
hopefully also representatives from
marketing sales service maybe management
and together you can then decide ok how
you gonna take this forward if you're
running out of time
are there any features any areas of
product functionality that your
functional functionality you can thin
out but you can drop some of the
detailed functionality or can you find
identifying other requirements that are
maybe easier it cheaper faster to
implement so those dos those
conversations to form part of the
release planning process and as I said a
good point in time to have those
conversations is in the sprint review
meeting and so I think at the beginning
we talked briefly about one project
owner project owner teams or large
projects what do you think were the
typical problems in in larger projects
with these kind of doing product
management the agile way I'm tempted to
say avoid large projects if you can okay
you know part of the the beauty of using
focusing on the minimal marketable
product in a product with minimum
functionality is that it allows you to
reduce the project size if therefore
reduces the investment risk you take but
but I also know that some projects some
products require a large approaching
project simply because of the the
inherent complexity they have the thing
you want to watch out for is then you
don't necessarily start with five six
seven eight nine ten or more teams that
you slowly grow your project and that
technique is called organic growth so
the idea is to start with ideally one
team and then slowly grow the project
from that one team that sort of forms
the original seat if you want so your
original project cell and then gets
split into two teams new people join
those uniformed teams and again they
then get split and the good thing about
this is that this gives a small team or
small thinker gives the original team
and therefore you know very small
project the opportunity to a do the
visioning and maybe stop the initial
product backlog and builds the first few
product increments and establish the
standards for the product and the
project and it also makes sure that you
pass on the knowledge so that's that's a
general scaling strategy that III find
helpful to be aware of that there's
another thing you that I find helpful in
that is that we have a preference in the
agile world to use what's called feature
teams over component teams and feature
teams are teams that implement features
such as themes groups of user stories so
you know it's all pieces of
functionality in the reason is that we
prefer feature teams is that they
typically have less dependencies than
component teams component teams are
teams that are focused on components or
subsystems so they can can can work with
less dependencies and they actually able
to create value a component team in
isolation can create value component
teams always always has to rely on other
component teams and integrate with their
work results in order to be able to have
something that can be can be shown to to
a customer or user so again you know
something to be aware of to think about
the project organization and consider
this preference of using feature teams
in terms of agile product management and
product ownership as of as I've said
before make sure there is one product
owner who acts as the overall or chief
product owner so even if you used a
small product owner team with two three
product owners one of them has to be the
overall or chief product owner and it's
not that we that we're looking for the
big leader the big decision maker we
just want to make sure that there's one
person in charge of the overall project
and overall product who facilitates
decision-making who takes care of the
overall product backlog grooming process
and release planning process includes
things together and if the product
owners can't jointly make a decision
can't agree there has to be one person
that says ok this is the way we're doing
things yes you're likely to need more
product owners multiple product owners
on a large project
do make sure those prod owners
communicate well and collaborate well
also make sure you have one product
backlog for your product and make sure
you use one release plan so I find that
one product backlog and one release plan
helps to integrate the different views
and helps to make sure that the teams
align and identify themselves as much
with the overall product and project as
with their team and features or
components that they implement so I
think we come to the end of the episode
so any any other pearls of wisdom you
would like to share with our listeners
pearls of wisdom well maybe maybe maybe
two things that the first one the first
thing I'd like to say is don't make the
mistake of thinking I'll you know this
product owner this is just another roll
and you know if people are called
product managers our product lioness it
doesn't really matter so let's just
rebrand all the product managers but
nothing else changes they're still far
away from the development teams they're
still limited the collaboration they
still don't take responsibility of
managing the product backlog that will
be a shame and that will be a
misunderstanding of what the product
owner of all is a product owner grohl is
about in the product owner role for a
scrum based agile project management
approach really is a cornerstone it's
really a key piece you've got to get
right so make sure you understand what
the product owner role is all about make
sure you select the right people and you
empower and trust those people properly
so that's the first thing and there's
the second thing I'd like to say is that
fully establishing out our product
management is likely to cause some
change it's likely to be disruptive and
it's likely to imply some form of
organizational changes such as adjusting
development plans career path employee
selection criteria in can similar things
you'll have to ask yourselves as an
organization where should provide owners
come from you know I mean being a
product owner is essentially a product
or project specific role there's nothing
wrong with product managers product
market
and other other job roles people playing
on filling those Charles moving into the
product owner role but that's that's one
of the questions you have to answer so
don't be surprised if it takes a while
to establish at your product management
than if it requires some changes in
otherwise I just hope that agile project
management techniques help you build
great products that become very
successful and help their customers and
users and that you'll have a lot of fun
building those products great thank you
all known for being on the show and good
luck for you for your book well thank
you very much it was a pleasure okay so
before we come to the real end of the
episode just a quick short remark at the
end home and we'll give away three
copies of his new book on enter product
management with scrum to our listeners
all you need to do to win one of those
copies is to follow us on Twitter Follow
as a radio on Twitter and retweet the
announcement of this episode with the
additional tag a PMS for agile project
management with scrum so add an hash a
PMS to your retweet of the announcement
of this episode and Holman will we'll
take a look at those things and draw
those three winners and we will announce
the winners via Twitter so have fun and
good luck for winning the book thanks
for listening to software engineering
radio software engineer radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by our website or you can advertise for
se radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious links and thus
left of button to contact the team
please send email to team at se - radio
net or if you're specific to an episode
please use the comments facility on the
website so other people can react to
your
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
Creative Commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pot site Music
Network for the music used in this show
the song is called Vegas
[Music]